Chapter 52.
the albatross.
Southeastward from the Cape, off the distant croettes, a good cruising ground
for right whalemen, a sail loomed ahead, the gon albatross by name. As she slowly
drew nigh, from my lofty perch at the forehead, I had a good view of that
sight so remarkable to a tyro in the far ocean fisheries, a whaler at sea, and
long absent from home.
As if the waves had been fullers, this craft was bleached like the skeleton of
a stranded walrus. All down her sides, this spectral appearance was traced with
long channels of reened rust, while all her spars and her rigging were like the
thick branches of trees furred over with horrost. Only her lower sails were set.
A wild sight it was to see her long bearded lookouts at those three mast
heads. They seemed clad in the skins of beasts, so torn and be patched the
raignment that had survived nearly four years of cruising. Standing in iron
hoops nailed to the mast, they swayed and swung over a fathomless sea. And
though, when the ship slowly glided close under our stern, we six men in the
air came so nigh to each other that we might almost have leaped from the mast
heads of one ship to those of the other.
Yet those forlornl looking fishermen, mildly eyeing us as they passed, said
not one word to our lookouts, while the quarter deck hail was being heard from
below. Ship aoy, have you seen the white whale?
But as the strange captain leaning over the pallet bull works was in the act of
putting his trumpet to his mouth, it somehow fell from his hand into the sea,
and the wind now rising a man, he in vain strove to make himself heard
without it. Meantime his ship was still increasing the distance between. While
in various silent ways the seammen of the Peekquad were avincing their
observance of this ominous incident, at the first mere mention of the white
whale's name to another ship, Ahab for a moment paused. It almost seemed as
though he would have lowered a boat to board the stranger, had not the
threatening wind for bad. But taking advantage of his windward position, he
again seized his trumpet, and knowing by her aspect that the stranger vessel was
a Nantucketer, and shortly bound home, he loudly hailed, "Ahoy there. This is
the Peekquad, bound round the world.
Tell them to address all future letters to the Pacific Ocean, and this time 3
years, if I am not home, tell them to address them, too."
At that moment the two wakes were fairly crossed, and instantly then, in
accordance with their singular ways, sholes of small, harmless fish, that for
some days before had been placidly swimming by our side, darted away with
what seemed shuddering fins, and ranged themselves for and a with these
strangers flanks. Though in the course of his continual voyagings, Ahab must
often before have noticed a similar sight, yet to any monomomaniac man, the
various trifles capricciously carry meanings. "Swim away from me, do you?"
murmured Ahab, gazing over into the water. "There seemed but little in the
words, but the tone conveyed more of deep helpless sadness than the insane
old man had ever before.
But turning to the steersman, who thus far had been holding the ship in the
wind to diminish her headway, he cried out in his old lion voice, "Uphelm! Keep
her off! Round the world! Round the world! There is much in that sound to
inspire proud feelings!" But whereto does all that circumnavigation conduct?
only through numberless perils to the very point once we started where those
that we left behind secure were all the time before us. Were this world an
endless plane and by sailing eastward we could forever reach new distances and
discover sites more sweet and strange than any cichlides or islands of King
Solomon. Then there were promise in the voyage. But in pursuit of those far
mysteries we dream of, or in tormented chase of that demon phantom that
sometime or other swims before all human hearts, while chasing such over this
round globe, they either lead us on in barren mazes or midway leave us wellelmed.